Contact

9867433838 (Mobile) karthik_balakrishnan@hotmai l.com

www.linkedin.com/in/karthik-b (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Business Strategy
International Sales
Key Account Management

Languages

English (Full Professional)
Hindi (Professional Working)
Tamil (Native or Bilingual)

Honors-Awards

Best Region Award Monsanto Pledge Award 2016 W3 Best-in-Show Award for mahindra.com

Publications

How 'Rise' became a rallying cry

Karthik Balakrishnan

Chief Executive Officer, The Printers Mysore Bengaluru, Karnataka, India

Summary

Karthik is the Chief Executive of The Printers Mysore, one of India's leading media companies. His mandate to drive strong business growth and re-cast the company into a future-ready, digital-era media powerhouse.

Karthik brings deep Sales, Operations, Strategy and Marketing experience into his current role. His strengths lie in strategy formulation, developing high-performing teams, driving business transformation, building brands, delivering digital makeovers - all this with a strong focus on execution excellence.

In his current role, Karthik's key short-term priorities are building people capabilities & a performance-oriented culture, driving operational efficiencies & cost consciousness, revamping the company's digital presence, developing a strong customer focus and securing financial results to support future growth. In the longer term, Karthik's focus is driving robust business growth, securing sustainable sources of long-term competitiveness, developing market-leading brands, creating a great place to work that attracts top talent and making the company a benchmark in the digital media space.

Prior to his current role, Karthik spent 8+ years with the Mahindra group in Mumbai. In his last role with the group, he was the custodian of the corporate brand. He has led several strategic pan-group programs in brand strategy development, global brand building, brand architecture strategy, movement marketing campaigns, employer branding, social & digital marketing programs.

Prior to joining Mahindra in 2008, Karthik spent 11 years in Sales and Marketing in companies like Monsanto, Lafarge and Dabur Ayurvet. He has worked in diverse markets in B2C and B2B sales; channel and key accounts management; domestic and

export operations amongst others. He has an impressive roster of achievements and awards in his stint with these companies.

Karthik has a degree in Agricultural Sciences from UAS, Bangalore and a post-graduate diploma in Management from IIM Ahmedabad.

Experience

Mahindra Rise

The Printers Mysore Chief Executive Officer May 2017 - Present Bengaluru Area, India

The Printers Mysore (publishers of Deccan Herald & Prajavani) is one of Karnataka's oldest media house, having been founded in the 1940s.

The mandate for this role is to drive strong business growth and re-cast the company into a future-ready, digital-era media powerhouse.

6 years 9 months

Vice President - Marketing

August 2014 - April 2017 (2 years 9 months)

Mumbai

The custodian of the corporate brand, Mahindra. Tasked with the key responsibility of making "Mahindra" a globally admired brand.

During the two years in the role, I helped set up a "Digital Command Centre" at the group level, drove the implementation of marketing automation systems, developed & launched a long-term global brand building campaign, built an ecosystem of innovative digital & social properties, set up a content marketing team, and drove action programs from the aspiration roadmap.

This tenure witnessed Mahindra winning a couple of global web awards, a dramatic improvement in digital metrics across a range of web & social properties and a jump in the Mahindra brand value from \$2.4 billion to ~\$3.0 billion

Also led marketing efforts for Mahindra's Racing - Moto3 and Formula E - platforms with the objective of growing a tribe of Mahindra Racing fans and building brand Mahindra in key global markets.

Sr.General Manager - Corporate Brand Management August 2012 - July 2014 (2 years)

Led a key strategic project to define a brand architecture strategy at the group level, completely overhaul the brand's visual identity, develop a brand voice and develop a set of brand guidelines. Executed the successful group-wide transition to the new identity.

Led a valuation exercise for brand "Mahindra". Worked with key group companies to translate findings from the brand strength scores into concrete action plans on a market segment-wise basis.

Developed and executed advertising programs in India; managed domestic and global sponsorships. Conceptualised and launched India's biggest innovation challenge - the USD \$1 million Rise Prize.

General Manager - Corporate Brand Management August 2010 - July 2012 (2 years)

Led a cross-functional, cross-business team that worked on re-defining the "Mahindra" brand and the development of strategic change programs to bridge brand and business. Worked extensively in developing internal communication programs, employee training, employer brand development and the development of social media presence at the group level.

Developed and executed advertising programs in India; managed key sponsorships.

Conceptualised and launched "Spark the Rise", a digital-driven movement marketing campaign that launched the re-positioned Mahindra brand. Built a community of 300,000+ change-agents within a short period of 18 months.

Mahindra & Mahindra
DGM - Corporate Strategy
July 2008 - July 2010 (2 years 1 month)
Mumbai Area, India

Consulted with the group's business sectors in Energy, Media, Defence and Agri-business. Worked on several projects of strategic importance that

included new business entry, inorganic growth opportunities, long term strategic roadmap etc.

Dabur Ayurvet Limited
General Manager (Sales & Marketing)
February 2006 - June 2008 (2 years 5 months)
New Delhi Area, India

Head of the Domestic & International Sales Operations and Marketing for a range of herbal animal health products. Led a team of 145 people across domestic & export markets and in the technical, sales and marketing functions. A significant amount of time was spent in reversing years of stagnant domestic sales, motivating and re-structuring the sales force, growing export sales and in improving the distribution system. Delivered a 33% growth in domestic sales and a 25% increase in exports in the two year tenure. Instilled financial discipline; significantly reduced the receivables and inventories of the company by 20% and 33% respectively (in 07/08 compared to 06/07)

Lafarge Cement

1 year 8 months

Regional Sales Manager April 2005 - February 2006 (11 months)

Managed the largest Sales region for the company - Bihar, Jharkhand, UP and Delhi

Led a team of 32 people across Sales, Technical, Logistics and Accounting to manage revenue

responsibility of Rs.400 crores through channel and institutional sales. Led a drive to significantly strengthen distribution, resolve long-pending CFA and channel issues, a drastic reduction in inventory and receivables - all this during a slump period in the cement industry. Operational improvements and channel strengthening during tenure resulted in a +20% sales growth in the region in the subsequent financial year

Sr.Manager - Institutional Sales July 2004 - March 2005 (9 months)

Head of Institutional (B2B) sales, overseeing revenues of Rs.200 crores. Established strong lead-in and lead-management systems, built a B2B sales team and put together a CRM system to drive sales growth. Built strong relationships and business with almost all major national Construction majors operating in the Eastern part of the country.

Monsanto India

7 years 2 months

Regional Business Manager

November 2002 - July 2004 (1 year 9 months)

Managed Sales & Operations in the states of Tamil Nadu and Kerala. Drove a 60% topline and a three-fold bottomline growth that lifted the region from 11th place (out of 12 regions in the country) to the No.1 position in a short span of 18 months. The region's impressive performance involved team re-structuring, building team capabilities, channel strengthening, a strong focus on sales discipline and driving operational efficiencies

Product Manager

January 2000 - October 2002 (2 years 10 months)

Managed the Rs.40 crore in annual sales Acetanilide family of herbicides in addition to identifying and commercialising new products. Directly managed several key marketing/distribution relationships with other large MNC's like DuPont, BASF etc. Successfully launched two new products to tap two new segments, thereby driving strong portfolio revenue growth of nearly 30% within 18 months.

Area Manager

July 1998 - December 1999 (1 year 6 months)

Bangalore

Managed sales operations for North Karnataka, one of the largest markets for the company. In a short period, drove a 20% y-o-y revenue growth, significantly improved operational - inventory and receivables - parameters and grew Corn seed sales from next-to-nothing to a level from where the brand became a market leader by 2001.

Management Trainee

June 1997 - June 1998 (1 year 1 month)

Bangalore

Moved across Sales, Marketing Services and Operations functions, gaining valuable experience working in the trenches

Education

Indian Institute of Management, Ahmedabad PGDM, Marketing · (1995 - 1997)

University of Agricultural Sciences, Bangalore B.Sc (Ag), Agriculture · (1990 - 1994)